Guide to the Davenport family papers, 1800-1941.
Davenport family papers, 1800-1941.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Davenport family papers, 1800-1941.
1173
41.2 cubic ft; 29 v.; 2 reels movie film; 3 oversize folders.
Correspondence, accounts, deeds, mortgages, tax statements, wills, bonds, stock certificates, bills, receipts, business and legal papers, maps, photographs, and movie films.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
The collection pertains chiefly to investments in lands in New York State, Illinois, Iowa, Kansas, Michigan, Minnesota, and Nebraska, to interests in mining, railway, mercantile, banking, and other business ventures, and to the settlement of family estates.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Correspondence, accounts, deeds, mortgages, tax statements, wills, bonds, stock certificates, bills, receipts, business and legal papers, maps, photographs, and movie films of the Davenport family of Angelica, Allegany County, New York and Bath, Steuben County, and of related Cameron, Waterman, French, and other families. Featured most prominently are Charles and Ira Davenport, and their agent, J. W. Waterman. The collection pertains chiefly to investments in lands in New York State, Illinois, Iowa, Kansas, Michigan, Minnesota, and Nebraska, to interests in mining, railway, mercantile, banking, and other business ventures, and to the settlement of family estates. Includes papers of the Davenport Home for Girls (also known as the Davenport Home for Female Orphan Children), Bath, New York, and the Bath Presbyterian Church.
Topics include western and frontier land speculation and investment, family relations, the problems of amassing capital and absentee ownership, banking, land taxation, forestry, and other matters pertaining to land ownership and management.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Davenport family.; Cameron family.; Davenport, Charles.; Davenport, Ira.; French family.; Waterman family.; Waterman, J. W.; Bath Presbyterian Church (Bath, N.Y.); Davenport Home for Female Orphan Children (Bath, N.Y.); Davenport Home for Girls (Bath, N.Y.)
Subjects:
Real property--New York (State); Real property--Illinois.; Real property--Iowa.; Real property--Kansas.; Real property--Michigan.; Real property--Minnesota.; Real property--Nebraska.; Real estate investment--New York (State); Real estate investment--Illinois.; Real estate investment--Iowa.; Real estate investment--Kansas.; Real estate investment--Michigan.; Real estate investment--Minnesota.; Real estate investment--Nebraska.; Business enterprises--New York (State)--Steuben County.; Business enterprises--New York (State)--Allegany County.; Commerce--New York (State)--Steuben County.; Commerce--New York (State)--Allegany County.; Banks and banking--New York (State); Mines and mineral resources.; Mineral industries.; Railroads--New York (State); Family--New York (State)--Steuben County.; Family--New York (State)--Allegany County.; Orphanages--New York (State)--Bath.; Administration of estates--New York (State)--Steuben County.; Administration of estates--New York (State)--Allegany County.; Forests and forestry--New York (State)--Bath.
Places:
Bath (N.Y.)--Economic conditions.; Angelica (N.Y.)--Economic conditions.; Bath (N.Y.)--Religious life and customs.
Form and Genre Terms:
Account books.; Deeds.; Mortgages.; Maps.; Photographs.; Motion pictures.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
RELATED MATERIALS
Consists of collections #539, #581, #1173, #1825, #1903.
CONTAINER LIST
- Bath Presbyterian Church drawings, 1945 (Folder 1)
- 1841-Dec. 1872 (Box 1)
- Jan. 1873-Feb. 1877 (Box 2)
  Also, statement of Ira Davenport in account with church trustees, June 1903, and typed copy of clause #5 in John Davenport's will re money given for upkeep of the church
  Other items included with these papers are patterns for the tile flooring (6 items) advertisments for stoves and furnaces (2 items), and one undated and unsigned pen and ink sketch of church steeple done on ordinary paper
- Mar. 1877-Jan. 1882 (Box 3)
- Jan. 1882-Jan. 1887 (Box 4)
- Feb. 1887-Dec. 1888 (Box 5)
- Jan. 1889-Oct. 1891 (Box 6)
- Nov. 1891-May 7, 1895 (Box 7)
- May 8, 1895-May 1, 1897 (Box 8)
- June 1897-Dec. 1898 (Box 9)
- Jan. 1899-July 1901 (Box 10)
- Aug. 1901-Sept. 1903 (Box 11)
- Oct. 1903-Aug. 1927 (Box 12)
- Bath Presbyterian Church Material (Box 13)
  Receipts (27 items) issued to the Presbyterian Church of Bath by Mould, New York City architect, June 15, 1874-Feb. 1875, showing payments made to him in payment for professional services by John and Ira Davenport on behalf of the church. One statement of account, June 15, 1874-Oct. 29, 1874. Series of letters from the offices of the architect in chief of the "Compania de Obras Publicas y Fomento del Peru," Lima to John Davenport, Oct. 20, 1875; Jan. 20, 1876; Apr. 20, 1876; May 19, 1876; July 21, 1876; and Sept. 20, 1876, concerning Mould's plans for the interior of the Bath church, the delivery of paper tracings of designs for stained glass, door hinges, chancel screen, pulpit, cornices, and other details, and financial arrangements being made. Fair copy of one letter from John Davenport to Mould, May 27, 1876, re plans for interior. Receipt, May 8, 1876. Six architectural drawings submitted to church trustees by Mould, 1874-1875. Printed professional advertisment of Mould, 1869
  The following drawings have been removed from the folder entitled "Architect's Drawings and Plans, 14 pieces," and placed in oversize map cases (in K map case K-9). They have been filed flat in bond paper between cardboard and marked #1173+
  #56 - Details of Pewing (Carpenter's contract), no date
  #99 - Details of stained glass for windows, in colour, Dec. 3, 1875
  #100 - North and South Elevations showing placement of stained glass, Dec. 4, 1875
  Details of windows (Stonework), Dec. 13, 1875; Stonecutter's details of door and window arches, June 17, 1874; Front elevation showing Tower and Wing as proposed to be built, no date
- Envelopes from collection (Box 14)
- Davenport Family Account Books, 1846-1931; 21 Volumes (Box 15-17)
  1854-1903
  1904-1905
  1881-1891
  1874-1884
  1877-1904
  1874-1906
  1883-1909
  1870-1906
  1899-1905
  1870-1931
  1881-1890
  1868-1903
  1865-1900
  1846-1904
  1869-1905
  1867-1893
  no date
  1899-1931
  1885-1899
  1891-1931
  1868-1893